Go on, eat up. They are known for their tasty weisswurst.
Hadi, yiyin. Buranın sosisi meşhurdur.
Like it? That's pretty good, huh?
Sevdiniz mi? Çok güzel, değil mi? Adın Dieter, değil mi?
You eat up too, or Dieter will finish it off before you get any.
Sen de ye yoksa Dieter hepsini bitirecek.
There is no need to worry, Dr. Tenma.
Endişelenecek bir şey yok Dr. Tenma.
It's safe here. Only regulars ever come here.
Burası güvenli. Buraya sadece müdavimler gelir.
If anyone new tries to come in,
Yeni biri gelmeye çalışırsa
Otto here will toss them out.
Otto onu dışarı atar.
If I always did that, I'd be out of business.
Hep öyle yapsaydım batardım.
-Who ordered the spätzle? -That was me.
-Spätzle kimin? -Benim.
I set up a bed in the attic.
Tavan arasına yatak koydum.
You'll sleep fine there if you don't mind the mice.
Fareleri sorun etmezsen güzelce uyursun.
Thank you, Otto.
Sağ ol Otto.
He seems like a grump, but he's a nice guy.
Aksi görünse de aslında iyi adamdır.
Well, you can't fight on an empty stomach.
Aç karnına savaşılmaz, değil mi?
Thank you for getting me a place to stay.
Bana kalacak bir yer ayarladığın için teşekkürler.
I should be thanking you.
Asıl ben teşekkür ederim.
If you hadn't saved me, I would be in the morgue now.
Beni kurtarmasaydın şu an morgda olurdum.
Cheating death makes this meal even more delicious.
Ölüme meydan okuyunca bu yemek daha nefis geliyor.
Go on, eat up.
Hadi, yiyin.
I've contacted Dr. Gillen.
Dr. Gillen'i aradım.
He's also relieved that we found you.
Seni bulduğumuza o da sevindi.
He placed an ad in the papers to try to contact you.
Sana ulaşmak için gazeteye bir ilan verdi.
"Let us reminisce about when we cheated."
"Nasıl kopya çektiğimizi konuşalım"
Have you seen it?
İlanı gördün mü?
Yes.
Evet.
Then why didn't contact him?
O zaman onunla neden irtibata geçmedin?
I didn't want you to get him caught up in this.
Seni bu olaya bulaştırmak istemedim.
That's what friends are for, especially at times like this.
Arkadaşlar bunun için vardır. Özellikle böyle zamanlarda.
Earlier, you said you were keeping an eye on me.
Bana göz kulak olduğunu söylemiştin.
That's because of the Richard Braun incident.
Richard Braun olayından dolayı.
Richard's case?
Richard'ın davası mı?
Yes. While he was on the police force,
Evet, Richard polis teşkilatındayken
he shot and killed that young serial murder suspect.
genç bir seri katil şüphelisini vurup öldürmüş.
When I was reading the article about it,
O olay hakkında bir haber okurken
Dieter saw the photo of the young man who was shot.
Dieter vurulan gencin fotoğrafını gördü.
He said that boy was at Kinderheim 511.
O çocuğun 511. Yetimhane'de olduğunu söyledi.
What's Kinderheim 511?
511. Yetimhane nedir?
An orphanage in East Berlin.
Doğu Berlin'de bir yetimhane.
A very special one.
Çok özeldir.
Dieter's foster father was one of the instructors there.
Dieter'ın koruyucu babası orada bir eğitmendi.
He had photos of all the children who had lived there.
Orada yaşamış çocukların fotoğrafları vardı.
This orphanage played a part in these things?
O yetimhanenin bir parmağı mı var?
Johan was there too.
Johan da oradaydı.
Do you mean there's a connection between the boy Richard shot and Johan?
Richard'ın vurduğu çocukla Johan arasında bir bağ mı var yani?
I'm not sure.
Emin değilim.
Before I was able to get any details from Richard, he died.
Richard ondan bilgi alamadan öldü.
It was at his grave that I spotted you.
Seni onun mezarında gördüm.
Poor Richard…
Zavallı Richard…
It's almost as if he brought us together.
Sanki bizi bir araya getirdi.
So far, you've had to fight alone.
Şimdiye kadar tek başına savaşman gerekti
But you're not alone anymore.
ama artık yalnız değilsin.
We'll prove your innocence.
Masum olduğunu kanıtlayacağız.
Johan isn't far. I have a photo.
Johan uzakta değil. Bir fotoğrafı var.
Darn it all.
Lanet olsun.
I must've left it in the office.
Ofiste bırakmış olmalıyım.
If you had seen the photo, that would've solved everything.
Fotoğrafı görseydiniz her şey çözülürdü.
The man who came to kill you probably found it.
O fotoğrafı muhtemelen seni öldürmeye gelen adam bulmuştur.
Then it's gone now.
O zaman gitti.
His name was Hess. I provided counseling to him and his wife.
Adamın adı Hess. Karısıyla birlikte danışanım olur.
I checked their number,
Numaralarına baktım
but when I called, there was nobody there named Hess.
ama aradığımda Hess adında kimse yoktu.
So, Johan isn't far.
Yani Johan uzakta değil.
Then I'll be able to see him. Right?
O zaman onu görebileceğim, değil mi?
Right.
Evet.
I'll be able to see Johan face to face.
Johan'la yüz yüze gelebileceğiz.
Thalbach & Schuwald AG.
Thalbach & Schuwald AG.
This is the main company in the Schuwald conglomerate.
Schuwald Holding'in ana şirketi bu.
Schuwald rarely ever shows his face, but he's been around a lot more lately.
Schuwald yüzünü nadiren gösterir ama şu aralar daha çok ortalarda.
About this time every morning, he visits the subsidiary companies.
Her sabah bu saatlerde alt şirketleri ziyaret ediyor.
Richard found out before he died.
Richard ölmeden önce öğrendi.
Not just this company, but all the conglomerate's companies
Genç biri Schuwald'ın sağ kolu olduğundan beri
have grown immensely ever since a certain young man
Sadece bu şirket değil,
became Schuwald's, right-hand man.
holdingteki tüm şirketler büyük çapta büyüdü.
Here they come.
Geliyorlar işte.
The man in the wheelchair is Schuwald.
Tekerlekli sandalyedeki adam Schuwald.
The one pushing him is Karl.
Onu iten de Karl.
And then there is…
İşte orada…
So, that's him?
Evet, o mu?
No doubt about it.
Ta kendisi.
Good.
Güzel.
-This is the first time. -Huh?
-Bir ilk. -Ne?
This is the first time
Johan'ı ilk defa
I've seen Johan in broad daylight.
gündüz vakti görüyorum.
Is that right? Then let's bring it all out into the daylight!
Öyle mi? O zaman her şeyi gün yüzüne çıkaralım.
Now's our only chance.
Tek fırsatımız bu.
That's correct. Now's our only chance to prove your innocence.
Doğru. Masum olduğunu kanıtlamak için tek fırsatımız bu
However, you should remain in hiding in the attic of Otto's restaurant for now.
ama şimdilik Otto'nun restoranında tavan arasında saklanmalısın.
We'll prove your innocence soon.
Masum olduğunu çok yakında kanıtlayacağız.
Richard's file is around here somewhere.
Richard'ın dosyası buralarda.
Here it is.
İşte burada.
I'm glad I brought this home.
İyi ki eve getirmişim.
It won't be long now.
Çok az kaldı.
We're almost there, Richard.
Neredeyse bitti Richard.
We're on the verge of avenging your death.
Ölümünün intikamını almaya çok yaklaştık.
We have Johan in our sights.
Johan'a kilitlendik.
We also found Dr. Tenma, the key witness.
Kilit tanık Dr. Tenma'yı da bulduk.
All that's left…
Geriye bir tek…
All that's left is to find a witness to Richard's death that night.
Geriye bir tek Richard'ın öldüğü gece için bir tanık bulmak kaldı.
There must be someone.
Mutlaka birisi vardır.
Once we find them,
Onu bulduğumuzda
we can prove that it was Johan who was with Richard when he died.
Richard öldüğünde yanında Johan olduğunu kanıtlayabiliriz.
Even if we can't,
Kanıtlayamazsak bile
there's that student Fahren, who claimed he was Schuwald's son and killed himself.
Schuwald'ın oğlu olduğunu iddia edip intihar eden Fahren adlı bir öğrenci var.
If we could find the prostitute that Fahren visited, we could prove
Fahren'ın ziyaret ettiği hayat kadınını bulabilirsek
that it was Johan that was with him.
yanındaki kişinin Johan olduğunu kanıtlayabiliriz.
And that's not all.
Hepsi bu değil.
If we investigate the couple who claim to be Johan's parents,
Johan'ın anne babası olduğunu iddia eden çifti incelersek
I mean, we even found Johan Liebert's grave!
Johan Liebert'in mezarını bile bulduk.
We are closing the noose around this Johan's neck!
Johan'ın boynundaki halatı iyice sıkıyoruz.
You know, Dr. Tenma,
Biliyor musun Dr. Tenma,
looking at you reminds me of Richard.
sana bakınca Richard'ı hatırlıyorum.
It's like you are carrying the weight of the whole world on your shoulders.
Tüm dünyanın yükünü omuzlarında taşıyorsun sanki.
Remember, you're not alone.
Unutma, yalnız değilsin.
You have Dieter.
Dieter yanında.
And there is Dr. Gillen and me too.
Dr. Gillen var, üstelik ben varım.
Everything will be fine now. You can sleep soundly tonight.
Her şey yoluna girecek. Bu gece huzur içinde uyuyabilirsin.
I didn't want to get him caught up in this.
Seni bu olaya bulaştırmak istemedim.
This is the first time.
Bir ilk.
This is the first time I have seen Johan in broad daylight.
Johan'ı ilk defa gündüz vakti görüyorum.
Now's our only chance.
Tek fırsatımız bu.
Wait! Aren't you…
Dur, sen…
Get out now!
Çabuk, koş!
Hurry!
Çabuk!
Reichwein speaking.
Ben Reichwein.
Doctor, it's me, Gillen.
Doktor, benim, Gillen.
I'm on my way over.
Oraya geliyorum.
Where's Tenma now?
Tenma şu an nerede?
He's in the hideout I set up.
Ayarladığım bir yerde saklanıyor.
Make certain he knows he should not leave.
Oradan ayrılmaması gerektiğini mutlaka bilmeli.
Something's bothering me.
Canımı sıkan bir şey var.
-Something is bothering me too. -Really?
-Benim de var. -Cidden mi?
It seems to me that Dr. Tenma isn't going after Johan
Dr. Tenma'nın Johan'ın peşinde olmasının sebebi
to prove his innocence.
masum olduğunu kanıtlamak değil sanki.
I don't want to believe it, but I'm worried about the same thing.
İnanmak istemiyorum ama ben de aynı şeyden korkuyorum.
Dieter.
Dieter.
What are you doing here?
Burada ne işin var?
Tenma told me to come here.
Tenma buraya gelmemi söyledi.
Where's Tenma?
Tenma nerede?
-He left. -Where did he go?
-Gitti. -Nereye gitti?
-He's going to kill him. -Huh?
-Onu öldürecek. -Ne?
Tenma's going to kill him.
Tenma onu öldürecek.
Stop him!
Durdurun onu!
Mr. Reichwein, stop him!
Bay Reichwein, durdurun onu!
Tenma will end up a murderer!
Tenma katil olacak!
That's enough for today.
Bugün bu kadar yeter.
Don't be like that. I've got more for you, doc.
Böyle yapma. Sana vereceklerim bitmedi doktor.
Here's where it gets really interesting.
İşler asıl burada ilginçleşiyor.
No. You can tell me in detail about it next time.
Hayır, detayları sonraki görüşmemizde anlatırsın.
My murder of the third woman is the best of them all.
En iyisi üçüncü kadını öldürmem.
Come on, doc!
Yapma ama doktor.
It's amazing!
Harikadır.
You want to know what she sounded like when I wrung her neck?
Boynunu kırdığımda nasıl bir ses çıkardığını bilmek istersin.
Come on, doc!
Hadi ama doktor!
The story is great! You see, that woman…
Harika bir hikâyedir! O kadın…
Where have you gone, Tenma?
Nereye gittin Tenma?
At last, I've found you, Dr. Gillen.
Seni nihayet buldum Dr. Gillen.
Who are you?
Sen kimsin?
I am Lunge. I am with the BKA.
Ben Lunge. Federal Kriminal Polis Ofisindenim.
I've heard about your work.
Çalışmalarını duydum.
Several of the serial murderers who were my research subjects
Araştırma konum olan birkaç seri katili
were apprehended by you.
sen yakaladın.
And I've read your book.
Ben de senin kitabını okudum.
Why thank you.
Teşekkür ederim.
It's a remarkable work.
Muhteşem bir çalışma.
The Psychology of Transcendental Crime.
Üstün Suç Psikolojisi.
No other work examines
Seri katillerin zihinsel durumunu
the mental state of serial murderers as deeply as it does.
o kadar derinden inceleyen başka bir çalışma yok.
In particular, chapter three, the case study of Heinz Kaul,
Özellikle 262'le 294. sayfalar arası,
on pages 262 to 294.
üçüncü bölüm Heinz Kaul araştırması.
I was especially intrigued by the connection of his childhood trauma
Çocukluk travmasıyla işlediği suçlar arasındaki bağlantı
to the crimes he committed.
ayrıca ilgimi çekti.
My, you know it quite well.
Vay be, çok iyi biliyorsunuz. Böyle dikkatli okumanızdan onur duydum.
The way I investigate involves putting myself into the criminal's shoes
Benim soruşturma yöntemim kendimi suçluların yerine koymak
and thinking like they do so I can predict their actions.
ve onlar gibi düşünmektir. Böylece yapacaklarını tahmin edebilirim.
I can tell you are highly experienced.
Çok deneyimli olduğunuz belli.
I'd be glad to speak about it more when I have more time.
Daha çok vaktim olduğunda sizinle konuşmak isterim.
Since neither of us have much time, I'll ask you this now.
İkimizin de çok vakti olmadığı için size hemen şunu sorayım.
You've been visiting Munich a lot lately, haven't you?
Şu aralar Münih'e sık sık gidiyorsunuz, değil mi?
What about it?
Ne olmuş yani?
Please, have a seat. This won't take long.
Lütfen oturun. Kısa sürecek.
You met with the psychologist Dr. Reichwein the other day, right?
Geçen gün psikolog Dr. Reichwein'la görüştünüz, değil mi?
Yes. He was one of my professors from the university.
Evet, üniversitede profesörümdü.
At Düsseldorf University?
Düsseldorf Üniversitesi'nde mi?
Yes.
Evet.
When you attended Düsseldorf University,
Düsseldorf Üniversitesi'ndeyken
there was a very talented neurosurgeon in your class, correct?
sınıfınızda çok yetenekli bir beyin cerrahı vardı, değil mi?
What are you getting at?
Nereye varacaksınız?
Did you see Dr. Tenma?
Dr. Tenma'yı gördünüz mü?
What are you talking about?
Ne diyorsunuz?
"Let us reminisce about when we cheated, Rudy."
"O sınavda Rudy'den nasıl kopya çektiğimizi konuşalım"
You placed that classified ad in all major newspapers across the country
1 Mayıs ile 22 Mayıs arasında bu şifreli ilanı
I was quite surprised to find out
Sizin ve Dr. Tenma gibi çok başarılı öğrencilerin
that brilliant people like you and Dr. Tenma cheated as students.
öğrenciyken kopya çekmesine çok şaşırdım.
It's amazing what close friends will do.
Yakın dostların neler yaptıkları çok güzel.
I wouldn't say that Dr. Tenma and I were close friends at university.
Üniversitede Dr. Tenma'yla çok yakındık diyemem.
In May of last year in Oder Park,
Geçen sene mayıs ayında Oder Parkı'nda
with your help, the Velbert Police were able to surround Dr. Tenma
sizin de yardımınızla Velbert Teşkilatı, Dr. Tenma'nın etrafını sardı
and were on the verge of capturing him, but he got away.
ve onu az daha yakalıyordu ama Dr. Tenma kaçtı.
That's because the wire I wore malfunctioned.
Taktığım mikrofon arıza yaptı çünkü.
That may have been how you helped him escape.
Kaçmasına böyle yardım etmiş olabilirsiniz.
He… Dr. Tenma is innocent.
O… Dr. Tenma masum.
Is that so?
Öyle mi?
Try to listen to me with an open mind.
Açık fikirlilikle dinlemeye çalışın!
The murders of
Eisler Memorial Hastanesi müdürü cinayeti, Düsseldorf'ta üç cinayet,
the murder of a patient in a building under construction,
bir hastanın şantiye alanında öldürülmesi,
the murder in Heidelberg,
Heidelberg'teki cinayet
and the murders of middle-aged couples across Germany.
ve Almanya genelinde orta yaşlı çift cinayetleri.
None of those were committed by Tenma.
Bu cinayetleri Tenma işlemedi.
As a criminal psychologist,
Suçlu psikoloğu olarak
this is the conclusion I came to after interviewing Tenma personally.
Tenma'yla bizzat görüştükten sonra bu kanıya vardım.
I see.
Anlıyorum.
So, where is he now?
Peki şu an nerede?
He has run off again.
Yine kaçtı.
Why does he keep running?
Neden sürekli kaçıyor?
Why does he run if he's innocent?
Masumsa neden kaçıyor?
He's not running away!
Kaçmıyor!
Then why would he leave, even you, a close friend of his?
O zaman sizin gibi bir yakın arkadaşını bile neden terk eder?
I have proof that he's not the murderer.
Katil olmadığına dair bir kanıtım var.
Have a look at this.
Şuna bakın.
This is my analysis of all the details of this case.
Bu davanın tüm detaylarının analizi.
Quite a considerable job.
Çok kapsamlı bir çalışma.
So, do you understand now?
Artık anlıyor musunuz?
Yes.
Evet.
The odd death of Fahren, who claimed to be Schuwald's son.
Schuwald'ın oğlu olduğunu iddia eden Fahren'in tuhaf ölümü.
The strange death of Richard Braun, the ex-detective investigating this case.
Bu davayı soruşturan eski polis dedektifi Richard Braun'un garip ölümü.
The questions and rumors about Schuwald's illegitimate child.
Schuwald'ın gayrimeşru çocuğu hakkındaki sorular ve söylentiler.
There's a young man at the center of all these things.
Tüm bunların merkezinde bir genç var.
When questioned by the police, Tenma named him the real murderer.
Polis, Tenma'yı sorguya çektiğinde asıl katilin Johan Liebert
Johan Liebert.
olduğunu söyledi.
But a grave for this very same Johan Liebert was found in Bruntal.
Ama Bruntal'da Johan Liebert'e ait bir mezar bulundu.
What's more, the person who took over Richard Braun's investigation,
Dahası, Richard Braun'un soruşturmasını devralan Dr. Reichwein
Dr. Reichwein, was nearly killed the other day.
geçen gün az daha öldürülüyordu.
I understand quite well.
Çok iyi anlıyorum.
But you can't do it.
Ama yapamazsınız.
You'll never prove that these separate incidents are related.
Bu farklı olayların bağlantılı olduğunu asla kanıtlayamazsınız.
Tenma knows this quite well too, which is why he has disappeared.
Tenma da bunu çok iyi biliyor. Bu yüzden ortadan kayboldu.
Am I wrong?
Yanılıyor muyum?
I notice how you drum your fingers.
Parmaklarınızı vurduğunuzu fark ettim.
Don't let it bother you.
Buna takılmayın.
I just use it to help me remember.
Sadece hatırlamama yardım ediyor.
As a psychologist,
Bir psikolog olarak
I would say that your anxiety is manifesting in your finger drumming.
anksiyeteniz kendini parmaklarınızı vurmak olarak dışa vuruyor.
It's the same with me. But instead of drumming my fingers, I use this recorder.
Bende de aynı durum var.
But in your case, what you remember by drumming your fingers is
Ama sizin yönteminizle parmaklarınızı vurarak hatırladıklarınız
already tainted by your preconceptions.
ön yargılarınız tarafından etkileniyor.
I bet that's always how you've done your work.
Kesin hep böyle çalışıyorsunuzdur.
You believe your memory is faultless and that all your judgments are correct.
Hafızanızın kusursuz, kararlarınızın da doğru olduğunu düşünüyorsunuz.
Do you have a family?
Aileniz var mı?
What about hobbies?
Hobileriniz neler?
Or do you only live for your work?
Yoksa sadece iş için mi yaşıyorsunuz?
Have you ever made a mistake?
Hiç hata yaptınız mı?
I bet you're terrified of making a mistake.
Eminim hata yapmaktan ödünüz kopuyordur.
In your mind, Tenma must be a bad person.
Sizin kafanızda Tenma illa kötü biri olmalı.
If he were not, then your whole world would fall to pieces.
Kötü adam değilse tüm dünyanız başınıza yıkılır.
Face the truth!
Gerçekle yüzleşin.
This is a photo of Johan Liebert.
Bu, Johan Liebert'in fotoğrafı.
Can you prove that Tenma made up everything?
Tenma'nın her şeyi uydurduğunu kanıtlayabilir misiniz?
This young man…
Bu genç adam
where is he now?
şu an nerede?
He is a student at Munich University.
Münih Üniversitesi'nde öğrenci.
He is working as Schuwald's secretary now.
Schuwald'ın sekreteri olarak çalışıyor.
I would like to keep this photo, if I may.
İzniniz olursa bu fotoğrafın bende kalmasını istiyorum.
Leave the rest of this matter to the police.
Bu olayı artık polise bırakın.
I may have made a terrible mistake.
Korkunç bir hata yapmış olabilirim.
Where's Dr. Tenma now?
Dr. Tenma şu an nerede?
He should be in Munich.
Münih'te olmalı.
Lunge here.
Ben Lunge.
Contact the Munich Police. I need some people on this case immediately.
Münih Polisi'yle irtibata geç. Bu davaya derhâl birkaç kişi baksın.
Tenma is somewhere in Munich now.
Tenma şu an Münih'te bir yerde.
A sniper rifle?
Keskin nişancı tüfeği mi?
I have no idea what you're talking about.
Neden bahsettiğini bilmiyorum.
Mr. Heitmeyer at the mountain retreat in Füssen called you about it.
Füssen'de bir dağ evinde yaşayan Bay Heitmeyer seni aradı.
Ten thousand marks upfront.
10 bin mark peşin.
Here.
Al.
It won't be easy to get what you want, so give me a week.
İstediğini bulmak kolay olmayacak, bana bir hafta ver.
In the meantime, get that pasty body of yours into shape.
Bu sırada da bu çelimsiz vücuduna çekidüzen ver.
Even if you got the best tools,
Elinde en iyi teçhizat olsa bile
they are worthless if you cannot use them properly.
düzgün kullanamadığın sürece hiçbir işe yaramaz.
Now, for more news.
Şimdi haberler. Devlet Ticaret Odası Münih Elektronik Sanayi Ticaret Fuarı için
for political and business leaders from around the world
dünyanın dört bir yanından siyasi ve iş liderleri için
who are here for the Munich Electronics Industry Trade Show.
gösterişli bir resepsiyon verdi.
With the formation of the EU, Bavarian industries are aiming
AB'nin kurulmasıyla Bavyera sanayisi yeni medya ağı lideri olmayı hedefliyor.
which means this will be the largest trade fair yet.
Yani bu fuar en büyük ticaret fuarı olacak.
The reception was attended by Hans Georg Schuwald,
Resepsiyona son 20 yıldır
who has not appeared in public for the last 20 years.
halkın içinde görülmeyen Hans Georg Schuwald da katıldı.
He was greeted with resounding applause.
Büyük bir alkışla karşılandı.
Though Mr. Schuwald attended in a wheelchair,
Bay Schuwald tekerlekli sandalyeyle gelse de
he looked healthy and showed these world leaders
sağlıklı görünüyordu ve bir yere gitme niyeti olmadığını
he will be around for a while to come.
dünya liderlerine gösterdi.
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
Alt yazı çevirmeni: Ömür Gencer